Dr. Khalifa: [2:158]  ... commits no error by traversing ...
You see that?
[2:158]  ... commits no error ...
I'm glad I translated that, I would have been red-faced
if I didn't translate it this way.
So, God is saying in Quran, you commit no error by
encircling these places.
That it is not idol worship.
And it is similar to God's command to the angels to fall prostrate before Adam.
Dr. Khalifa: They were not worshipping Adam, they were obeying God.
A man: Are there prices (unintelligible)?
Dr. Khalifa: Prices?
A man: Practices, practices, (unintelligible) that people observe (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: No, I don't think of it (unintelligible)
A man: (unintelligible) and if you are in Mecca, someone told you to do something, "oh, you have to do this."
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. The only part is visiting the, the prophet's tomb, that is, that is idol worship.
That visiting the prophet tomb, going to the prophet's tomb and speaking to the prophet and all this, discard it.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A woman: I was gonna ask a question (unintelligible)
you talked about
(unintelligible) fast
(unintelligible) go on fasting
A man: to be able to (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Not (unintelligible) Hajj do not fast unless they break something
like when, when, if you break the Ihraam (sanctity)
and you cannot sacrifice a sheep, then you have to fast
Dr. Khalifa: like it says here.
A woman: (unintelligible) Yeah. Okay, well, why would (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Prophet. They shouldn't.
A woman: They shouldn't.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A man: Yeah, If we, if you were recommended by the Imam (unintelligible), you know, like, say, to fast like two days.
Dr. Khalifa: Sure, why not? It's from Hadith, yeah.
A man: Was that, was that...
A man: It's Sahih Hadith, and that's what I was referring to before like this
A man: fasting (unintelligible) going two days and (unintelligible), that's a Hadith.
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: [2:196] ... During the normal times of peace, if you break the state of sanctity between 'Umrah and Hajj, then expiate by offering a sacrifice. Those who cannot afford it may fast three days during Hajj and seven when they return home—thus completing ten— provided they do not live at the Sacred Mosque (Masjid). ...
Now, this means seven days when you go back.
But if you live there, then you're not going back.
Again, the Quran's language being perfectly, perfect.
[2:196] ... You shall observe GOD, and know that GOD is strict in enforcing judgement.
197 tells you that Hajj is to be observed,
remember I said on the eighth day you have to be there?
Because there are specified days.
[2:197]  Hajj shall be observed during the specified months.* Thus, whoever sets out to observe Hajj shall abstain from sexual intercourse, evil deeds, and arguments throughout Hajj. ...
So, this is really self-control.
You cannot say a word of cursing or anything.
You don't say any bad words.
You only say,
لَبَيْكُ اللَّهُمَّ لَبَيْكُ
I'm responding to You, my Lord.
[2:197]  ... Whatever good you do, GOD is fully aware thereof. As you take provisions for the journey, remember that the best provision is righteousness. You shall observe Me, O you who possess intelligence.
Dr. Khalifa: Okay, any questions on Hajj?
A man: Yes.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah
A man: So, how many days are (unintelligible) it's the Hajj?
Dr. Khalifa: The eighth, on the eighth you must be in Mecca, the ninth in 'Arafaat
two days (unintelligible) four days.
Dr. Khalifa: minimum.
A man: four days?
A man: The first day, so, this is encircling the Ka'aba and...
Dr. Khalifa: IN SHAA ALLAH
A man: (unintelligible)
A man: that can be done in one day, but...
Dr. Khalifa: That's not in one hour.
Dean Majul: Two hours.
A man: But
Dr. Khalifa: And then on the ninth, you must be on 'Arafaat.
A man: (unintelligible)
A man: What about the end of the days?
Dr. Khalifa: Two days in Mena.
Dr. Khalifa: It's coming up.
Dr. Khalifa: These are coming up in 203.
Dean Majul: Yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: Oh, in Mena, you're, you're stoning the Satan.
Stoning of Satan's ceremonies are in Mena.
Dr. Khalifa: That's right.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: No, I just remembered
that in Mena, you see, Satan was trying to talk Abraham out of sacrificing his son.
He says, "come on now, you're gonna kill your son. That doesn't make sense."
So, get going, get out, get out of here you Satan rejected.
Dr. Khalifa: It's so big.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: And so, we throw stones at Satan,
it's such a symbol of Satan's temptation to disobey God.
And it is done three times.
We throw seven stones every time,
first day and second day.
And all the people must be there.
So, we have one million people in Mena throwing stones.
Now, they made it easy by building bridges.
So, there are two, actually two storeys of people.
My parents couldn't do it, so I did it on their behalf.
But it's just too much of a crowd, and it's just,
if you're a certain age, you cannot do it.
So, I collected, let me see,
seven for myself, seven for my father, seven for my mother,
and there was another sick person who (unintelligible)
do it on his behalf.
Dr. Khalifa: I do four, I do it for four people, on their behalf.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: No, one at a time saying, Allahu Akbar, every time.
Dr. Khalifa: Say, Allahu Akbar. And you throw it.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: If you have somebody who'd like a bigger stone,...
Dr. Khalifa: Because nobody sees whoever who's throwing what.
A woman: Allahu Akbar.
Dr. Khalifa: Aim at his, aim at his head, you know.
Dr. Khalifa: It's funny, some people get carried away in that, (unintelligible)
because their, their guide is telling them,
just think of that as Satan.
And you are throwing stones at Satan.
So, some of them get carried away,
and they throw out their shoes and things.
But they, they really get carried away, honestly.
Dr. Khalifa: There's so many shoes on that thing.
A man: Is that a requirement?
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: Take off you, Satan.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Dr. Khalifa: What?
A woman: That's overwhelming what (unintelligible) said.
A woman: Allah didn't actually order Abraham.
Dr. Khalifa: Right. Never in the Quran did God order Abraham.
A woman: So,...
Dr. Khalifa: The Quran is very careful not to, it's very careful to say, or not to say that God ordered Abraham to kill his son.
A woman: So, you just said, for the devil tried to talk him out of...
Dr. Khalifa: Out of sacrificing his son.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Well, Satan knew that Abraham thinks, Abraham thinks God orders him
Dr. Khalifa: to sacrifice his son, and Abraham was going on that assumption, that God, that he's obeying God.
A woman: Ok.
Dr. Khalifa: So, the idea is to disobey God, because Abraham was convinced
that God wants him to, to kill his son.
Dr. Khalifa: Of course, this, the whole thing is God's will, it's a test.
A woman: Yes.
Dr. Khalifa: But the fact is, God did not order him to kill his son,
and obviously did not want him to kill his son,
because God intervened and saved his Ismail.
Thanks to our professor, Dean Majul, again.
So, the two days in Mena that will come up in 203,
you will be stoning Satan.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
Dr. Khalifa: Seven heavens and seven universes.
A woman: (unintelligible) like that yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A man: Seven Gates of Hell.
Dr. Khalifa: Seven Gates of Hell?
I don't know what the significance of number seven is.
Our, see this,
our world consists of seven universes.
The Hereafter will be eight Universes.
The eighth being Hell,
the farthest from God.
198.
[2:198]  You commit no sin by seeking commercial benefits during Hajj. When you file ...
Okay, now we're gonna stop at this sentence.
Let's say you're gonna take advantage of being in Hajj and,
buy wholesale a bunch of perfumes
to bring them here as a trade.
And you sell them to the Muslims.
You use perfume from Mecca.
Perfectly alright.
And you make a lot of money.
So, this is what this verse is saying.
[2:198]  You commit no sin by seeking commercial benefits during Hajj. When you file from 'Arafaat, ...
That's on the evening of the ninth day.
[2:198]  ... you shall commemorate GOD at the Sacred shrine (of Muzdalifah). ...
This is where you collect the stones,
the gravels.
You Pray,
you Pray the Maghrib and 'Eshaa, both.
And you collect forty-nine stones,
I think, seven, seven times seven
gravels.
What they do in Saudi Arabia, they go,
the trucks go to the places where these things are thrown.
They collect them and go back to Muzdalifah and dump them there.
Yeah.
And then, the people collect them and go throw them there.
And Saudi Arabia authorities, they collect them again.
The trucks go to Muzdalifah and dump them there.
[2:198]  ... commemorate God for guiding you; before such guidance, you were really astray.
[2:199]  You shall file together, with the rest of the people, and seek GOD's forgiveness. GOD is Forgiver, Merciful.
Now, filing from 'Arafaat or being on 'Arafaat
should remind you of the Day of Judgment.
The people are equal.
There is no rich, no poor.
And it's a (unintelligible), a great number of people,
one million people on the hill of 'Arafaat.
The Day of Judgment will be like this.
All past, present, future generations
will be up at the same time on this earth.
Dr. Khalifa: It's gonna be very crowded.
A woman: (unintelligible) crowds.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: And in 'Arafaat, it is that crowded.
So, it says, you shall fight together, because there is no distinction.
There is no distinction between rich and poor.
They will not reserve a special place in the Hereafter
for Raul (unintelligible), for example.
Dr. Khalifa: So, this is a presidential suite, remember that. There's no such thing.
A woman: (unintelligible).
Dean Majul: But I (unintelligible) you.
Dr. Khalifa: It's gonna be in deep trouble, actually.
A woman: Yeah.
Dean Majul: Ustaz (teacher)
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Dean Majul: I (unintelligible) you. (unintelligible) better.
Dean Majul: But if we're gonna become a Muslim,
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
Dean Majul: and he decides to go on the Hajj,
his (unintelligible) government
Dean Majul: will give the biggest threat for him.
Dr. Khalifa: Exactly. Yeah.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Oh, yeah. You win the bet.
Dr. Khalifa: That's right.
A woman: In this world.
[2:200]  Once you complete your duties of worship, you shall continue to remember GOD just as you remember your own parents, or even better. Some people may say, "Our Lord, give us in this life," while they have no share in the Hereafter.
[2:201]  Others would say, "Our Lord, let us be righteousness in this life, and righteousness in the Hereafter, and spare us the agony of Hell."
[2:202]  Each of these will reap the fruits of their work. And GOD is most efficient at reckoning.
Like, like I said, some people spend their life here seeking the materials of this world, concerned
about the blink of an eye,
and forgetting the eternal life.
Now, 203 are the final two days of Hajj.
[2:203]  You shall commemorate GOD during the specified days after Hajj; ...
Two to three days at Mena.
[2:203]  ... Thus, if you complete this in two days, you commit no error, and if you stay longer, you commit no error, so long as you maintain righteousness. ...
You see here the openness because sometimes it's impossible for you to leave Mena
when you want to. There's so many people and only a few buses.
So, you may not be able to leave
in two days.
But God says, it's perfectly alright.
Because when God says
the Wudu shall be that
four steps, then that's it. Four steps.
But when He says, it's okay to do it nine steps,
then it is okay nine steps.
But it doesn't.
So, the Quran is very careful
and takes all,
all circumstances into consideration.
[2:203]  ... You shall observe GOD, and know that you will be gathered before Him.
Where is your Jahan?
Okay.
I knew he was here, but I can't, I couldn't see him.
It's too close.
Ok. You take 2 - 0 - something. 204.
I was looking for him to start, (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Sorry, it's too (unintelligible)
A man: Yeah. (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible)
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: 204
A man: (unintelligible)
A man: Of course. Very nice. Alhamdu Lillah.
A woman: (unintelligible)
A man: Alhamdu Lillah.
Dr. Khalifa: Are you talking to me?
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. That's not the real you.
You're not comfortable are you?
It's more comfortably just, just casually.
Dr. Khalifa: Ok.
Jahan: [2:204]  Among the people, one may impress you with his rhetoric, may even call upon GOD to witness his intentions, while he is a most ardent opponent.
[2:205]  When he turns away, he roams the earth corruptingly, destroying properties and lives. GOD despises corruption.
[2:206]  Then, when told to observe GOD, sinful pride overtakes him. Consequently, his only destiny is Hell; a miserable abode.
[2:207]  Then there are those who readily devote themselves to attain GOD's pleasure, and GOD is most compassionate towards such worshipers.
[2:208]  O you who believe, you shall submit totally to God, and do not follow the steps of Satan. He is your ardent enemy.
[2:209]  If you regress, despite these profound revelations, then you know that GOD is Almighty, Wise.
[2:210]  Are they waiting until GOD Himself comes to them in dense clouds, together with the angels? If this happens, the whole matter will be terminated, and all things will be returned to GOD.*
Jahan: [2:211]  Ask the Children of Israel how many profound miracles have we manifested to them! For those who disregard God's favors after receiving them, GOD is most strict and forceful.
Dr. Khalifa: Great.
Jahan: [2:204]  Among the people, one may impress you with his rhetoric, may even call upon GOD to witness his intentions, while he is a most ardent opponent.
Dr. Khalifa: Appearances may be deceiving and (unintelligible)
Jahan: [2:205]  When he turns away, he roams the earth corruptingly, destroying properties and lives. GOD despises corruption.
[2:206]  Then, when told to observe GOD, sinful pride overtakes him. Consequently, his only destiny is Hell; a miserable abode.
Sinful pride (unintelligible)
Jahan: [2:207]  Then there are those who readily devote themselves ...
Dr. Khalifa: So, you tell them that they are, they are not following what God says,
they are sinful, they are taken, overtaken by sinful pride.
And I see these people all in front of me.
You share them the Quran and you say,
Here's what the Quran says about Wudu.
You say, this is how you do the ablution.
Dr. Khalifa: Is this how you do your ablution?
A woman: No.
Dr. Khalifa: They say, no.
And then, sinful pride overtakes, and they say,
What is wrong with having more?
And you say, you're disobeying God. You're not following what God says.
But you can see this, now, they think they're righteous.
And they, they call on God to witness,
they're talking about God and worshipping God and all this,
when really they are not.
Dr. Khalifa: How can they be worshipping God and not following His commandments?
A man: Worse yet is when you're doing it the right way and several thousand "you're supposed to do more."
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A man: I've had that happen to me (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Oh, yes, of course.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A man: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: And they are so righteous, you know.
A man: "Oh, you're not doing it completely right. You're gonna have more."
Dr. Khalifa: That's right.
Dr. Khalifa: Okay, Jahan.
Jahan: [2:207]  Then there are those who readily devote themselves to attain GOD's pleasure, and GOD is most compassionate towards such worshipers.
Jahan: [2:208]  O you who believe, you shall submit totally to God, and do not follow the steps of Satan. He is your ardent enemy.
Dr. Khalifa: No, I think there was no business, for example, as a submitter to God
[2:208]  ... you shall submit totally to God, ...
And this is what God says, this is what we do.
And that's not the question of fasting,
because God says you will fast the specified days of Ramadan and this is what we do.
You just strictly adhere to what God is saying.
You don't deviate.
Because Satan wants you to deviate.
God wants you to do something else.
Then, you have a god beside God,
who's telling you to do nine steps of Wudu, instead of four.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A woman: You know, in the following the steps of Satan, you know,
you can see that following the steps of Satan
A woman: is as in walking alone and saying what you think.
Dr. Khalifa: No.
A woman: But also (unintelligible)
Satan always adds more steps to everything.
A woman: He says, you do more Prayers, more Wudu, more this, more that.
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
A woman: And it's kind of like a double (unintelligible) with extra steps.
A woman: And I think that it's a really interesting word to cover that.
A woman: So, you could, you could blindly follow Satan as he leads you
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A woman: or you could, you know, take (unintelligible) unrighteous, and you follow all those extra steps, and, and (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: The idea is to let you disobey God. That's the whole idea.
Jahan: [2:209]  If you regress, despite these profound revelations, then you know that GOD is Almighty, Wise.
[2:210]  Are they waiting until GOD Himself comes down to them in dense clouds, together with the angels? If this happens, the whole matter will be terminated, and all things will be returned to GOD.*
(unintelligible)
Jahan: [2:211]  Ask the Children of Israel how many profound miracles have we manifested to them! For those who disregard God's favors after receiving them, GOD is most strict and forceful.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, what more,
what more do they want?
I mean, God parted the sea for them,
they walked across the Red Sea,
walked, no bridge.
There was no bridge.
Walked across the Red Sea, and then Pharaoh and his army follows, and the water closes on Pharaoh, and right before their eyes
and they still wanted to worship the calf.
Dr. Khalifa: And so, this is, these are the questions, and we are the same people.
A woman: We've got the same kind of miracles (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: We've got even more profound miracles.
We show that the Quran is from God, you know, what more, what more can we do?
Dr. Khalifa: Prove to them that this is from God.
Dean Majul: Yeah.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dean Majul: That's right.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Dean Majul: No, but some people are not satisfied, they would like to,
Dean Majul: they would like Allah
Dr. Khalifa: Exactly.
A woman: Yeah.
Dean Majul: to come (unintelligible) because it seems that
Dr. Khalifa: That's, this is exactly the question. And they're waiting...
Dean Majul: certainly 210 is connected with 211, it is in first.
Because as we know, the Jews have asked Moses,
Dean Majul: "Who is He? What's His name? We want to see Him."
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
Dean Majul: They want to see Allah.
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
Dean Majul: And yet, they were given so many things, so many favors from Allah,
and they were not satisfied.
And now, as you say, there are so many things in the Quran,
many things, and so many wonders, and still people are not satisfied.
Dean Majul: They would like Allah to come down in...
Dr. Khalifa: Right. Yeah, that's the question (unintelligible)
Dean Majul: It's a form of ingratitude, I think. It's a form of Kufr, ungratefulness towards Allah.
Dr. Khalifa: Definitely.
A woman: You know, last time I was telling this old man here about Quran and this thing
Well, this is God (unintelligible)
So, I gave him some references about when God (unintelligible)
(unintelligible)
but I always tell you, a big, big woman who was Jewish
I said, fine, if you can tell a big woman who is Jewish, you know,
A woman: it helps me to believe in God, that's probably okay
A woman: (unintelligible) I don't think that God's (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: blasphemous
A woman: What?! Not really.
In a way he was, but in a way he wasn't.
A woman: You know, somehow, so I said, I'll believe you if you could tell me what God looks like.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, this is what the Jews said to Moses.
A woman: Yeah, so I told them about God coming to the world and the light of the Lord,
and about how physical God was when He smashed that mountain
to Moses.
But that's all I can think of when it's your, if somebody says something like that to you
A woman: (unintelligible) I don't know what you're saying.
A woman: You say, you want your head to fall off?
Dr. Khalifa: Oh, it's Ok. "You're just being ridiculous" and walk out.
A man: So, what about mentioning holding seven universes in His hand?
A man: Can you even see how big?
A woman: I did that, too. I did that, too.
A woman: I did that, too. (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: He's just being a smart aleck.
Dr. Khalifa: Abib, you wanna take the 212 and 213?
Abib: The Hereafter (unintelligible)
[2:212]  This life is adorned in the eyes of the disbelievers, and thus they ridicule those who believe. However, the righteous will rank high above them on the Day of Resurrection. GOD blesses whomever He wills, without limits.
[2:213]  The people used to be one homogeneous congregation until GOD sent His prophets as preachers and the warners, and sent to them the scripture, the statute book. Ironically, those who received the scripture were the ones that disputed among themselves, utter serious sentiments for one another. As for those who believe, GOD guides them to the truth in accordance with His will, by leaving the others in dispute. GOD guides whoever He wills in the right path.*
The verse 212, well, it describes some people saying, you know, you only have one life to live, so
they could do whatever they want with this.
They think that this is the only life, and it's the greatest life of all, you know, so they live it up,
and, you know, do whatever is sinful,
playing with (unintelligible)
Jahan: But, in the Hereafter, you know, these people...
Dean Majul: It's all (unintelligible). The reward is there.
It's a matter of time, but what is time? That's, that's the blink of of an eye.
Dean Majul: There's a lot to say on, on this.
Dr. Khalifa: Also, the believers themselves would ask the question,
[2:214]  ... "Where is God's victory?" ...
Their question, their question tested until they ask the question.
Because we're really being persecuted, you know, for adhering to the Quran alone.
I was discussing today with one fellow,
Dr. Khalifa: the one person who was saying, Ameen.
A woman: Ameen.
Dr. Khalifa: That's right.
Dr. Khalifa: I was discussing with him. What's wrong with worshiping God alone?
That's the idea. You know, the persecution.
I, I haven't visited Egypt since a long time because of,
that's the idea, I miss my relatives and friends and so forth. I was talking to them.
And so, so, it's a form of persecution.
And I know you're all subjected to this when you meet the other people.
We just as believers are subject to persecution,
by relatives, friends.
This is part of the test.
We also come to the pressure of...
But you see, what they don't realize is that it's too late. Once you see the truth,
it's, it's, there is no return.
Dr. Khalifa: The point of no return.
A woman: What's good after this?
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. Alhamdu Lillah.
A woman: Yeah. Alhamdu Lillah.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Dr. Khalifa: Okay. Are there any questions?
No questions. (unintelligible)
We're also reading Al-Fãtehah.
Bism Allah Arrahman Arraheem (1:1)
Al hamdu Lillahi Rabbil ‘Alameen (1:2)
Arrahman Arraheem (1:3)
Maliki Yawm Eddeen (1:4)
Eyyaka Na’abudu Wa Eyyaka Nasta’aeen (1:5)
Ehdina Al-Serata Al-Mustaqeem (1:6)
Serata Al-Lazeena An’amta ‘Alayhim Ghayri Al-Maghdoobi ‘Alayhim Wa Laddaalleen (1:7)
We're gonna eat Masouda's cake that she made for Erol's return.
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible)
Dean Majul: We need, we need Erol's cake for the cake not from the Quran (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: It's also...
Dean Majul: (unintelligible)
Dean Majul: What time did you arrive?
Dr. Khalifa: There's Lorenzo's kid...
A man: ... Alal Salat. Hayya Alal Salat.
Hayya Alal Falah. Hayya Alal Falah.
Allahu Akbar. Allahu Akbar.
A man: La Elaha Ella Allah.
Dean Majul: Al-Salãmun ‘Alaykum Wa Rahmatullahi Wa Barakatu
Bism Allah Arrahman Arraheem
Alhamdu Lillah
ٱلْحَمْدُ لِلَّهِ ٱلَّذِى هَدَىنَا بالایمان
(unintelligible)
Ash-hadu Alla Elaha Ella Allah Wahdahu La Shareeka Lah
هو الله و له الحمد وَهُوَ عَلَى كُلِّ شَىْءٍ قَدِيرٌ
(33:41) يَٓأَيُّهَا ٱلَّذِينَ ءَامَنُوا ٱذْكُرُوا ٱللَّهَ ذِكْرًا كَثِيرًا
(unintelligible)
This is (unintelligible) in continuation of the last Khutba.
It seems that this series of (unintelligible)
ongoing, they're never ending.
Dean Majul: (unintelligible) what we had last time.
A woman: Yes.
Dean Majul: We found out or analyzed that Adam's disobedience was not sinful.
It was not a malicious form of disobedience.
We can even go further and say
that Adam had no intention of transgression.
Actually, it's clear in the Quran,
in Sura 20:115,
that what happened to Adam was that he forgot.
He was not strong enough.
[20:115]  ... he forgot, ...
We also learned in Sura 6, verse 68,
in Sura 12, verse 42,
in Sura 18, verse 63,
in Sura 58, verse 19, and so on
that the creature that makes us forget
the most important tree
is no less than Sheytan (Satan) himself.
Satan makes us forget.
And thus we can conclude
on the basis of these verses
that I have elaborated,
because Sheytan (Satan) who made
poor Adam, our great-great-grandfather, forget.
I think there's not much speculation to the point.
However, the fact that Adam forgot,
even temporarily,
leads us to assume
that he has forgotten something that he knew.
You cannot forget something that you never knew,
or you never know.
And thus we had some speculation last time,
and I submitted to you, brothers and sisters,
that what Adam forgot
was what Allah Himself Subhanahu Wa Ta'ala taught him.
And as you know, in Sura 2, verse 31,
it's very clear.
Allah taught Adam all the names.
I admit there was some Tafsir or commentary on this point.
I went further and said that these names
which Allah taught Adam
have to do with Allah Himself,
who Allah is, what Allah is,
His powers, more important,
that He is the source of all power.
And knowing these qualities of Allah,
denoted by His names,
gives us a profound, a deep form of knowledge.
It makes us understand the signs, the Ayas around us.
And not only the signs around us,
but the signs within us.
Quran speaks of the signs outside us,
without and within.
And if we know Allah's manifestations
without and within us,
a high form of knowledge, I'm insisting,
we will be able to see all phenomena
in its, the blue light,
natural phenomena, both physical and biological,
and within ourselves, psychological phenomena,
and what these, and what these psychological phenomena brings about,
individual and social phenomena.
And as I mentioned last time,
all of these things,
our birth, our childhood, our youth,
our death, our loss, our petty hatreds,
our resentment, emotions, tribulations,
all of these things,
even warfare between groups and so on,
all of these represent manifestations
of Allah's creative power.
He is the Ruler.
He rules everything.
And nothing can happen without His will.
Then, we talked also of Allah breathing
something of His Spirit into Adam.
It's very interesting.
On at least 3 points, Quran says
that Allah breathes into Adam
something
MIN (مِن) the Arabic word is
(32:9) مِن رُّوحِهِ
[32:9]  ... from His spirit. ...
But it's very important.
He did not say He blew His Spirit.
Because then,
Allah will be creating other Allahs,
which is a contradiction.
Something.
What does this mean?
Where we have this?
In Sura 15, verse 29.
In Sura 32, verse 9.
And in Sura 38, verse 72.
And this is what I believe, it's up
to you to reflect on what I'm saying,
to accept or reject my views,
or to use my views as a point of departure
for you to go deeper into it,
or find an alternative interpretation.
My interpretation is that
the breathing into Adam
something of His Spirit,
Allah's Spirit,
would be the following.
First,
the capacity,
the capacity to know,
to know the names themselves.
For if man does not have the capacity to know the names,
he cannot know.
This is very clear.
Let's say, A equals A.
In other words, Allah had given him
the capacity for knowledge,
any special knowledge,
knowledge to know about Allah Himself.
Allah is so great,
nothing can know Allah
unless something who knows Allah
has something given to him by Allah.
I hope this is very clear.
So, this is philosophical proof.
You cannot know Allah
unless Allah Himself has given you the power to know Him.
Because He is so great
and so above us,
no one less than Allah can know Him.
But Allah gave man
His part of His breath.
And this breath of Allah in us
is what allows us to know Allah. Alright?
Now, this is a very profound view.
I hope you will not
forget it.
But more than that,
it's not just a matter of giving man
the power to know Him.
Allah, I believe,
had given us
certain capacities
to manifest
some of the qualities
which we attribute to Him.
And the Quran is full of these attributes.
When the Quran says that
Allah destroys,
we all know we can destroy.
Can we destroy?
Why are we destroying things day after day?
And so,
we have no capacities.
This, I think, is a second,
but just as important meaning
of
the breath of Allah
in us.
And it's not that we just have these capacities.
Because the capacity can remain a capacity.
There must be certain actualities
in the relations between Allah
and mankind such that
these qualities can become
what we would call actual.
In other words,
we may have
the capacity
to feel pity or to love,
but that capacity can always,
will always remain a capacity.
Unless there is something
that will actualize that capacity
into something
that is real.
So,
if, if we have the capacity
for mercy,
that capacity
will remain a capacity.
It can only be actualized
on account of certain forces.
Allah Himself can help us,
or His Messengers can teach us
how to actualize
this capacity.
Incidentally, this point shows
the necessity of revelation.
So, I think we have said so much about these powers
to know,
these powers to be created,
these powers to destroy,
these powers
to have pity,
and to sympathize,
the ability
to have what we call
this fine sense of consideration.
And again,
let me say that
this breath from Allah
in mankind
represents
the most important parts
of man's complex nature.
Man is composed of clay,
but he also has life in him.
We attribute that to the soul.
But we also say,
based on the Quran,
that he partakes of the breath
for the Spirit of Allah.
This spirit in mankind
is the highest part,
the most excellent part,
of man's soul or not.
It cannot be otherwise,
for it comes from Allah Itself.
It does not belong to us,
although we are utilizing it.
And now we can understand deeper some of these verses in the Quran.
When Adam and Eve
say to Allah,
Allah,
we have wronged ourselves.
We have wronged ourselves.
What is the wrong?
Their feet, stomach, hair, and so on?
No, it's (unintelligible)
They realized that they had wronged
the most important part of themselves.
That's part which belongs to Allah.
And in trying to harm that part of Allah, actually, they ended up hurting themselves
because no one can harm Allah.
So, if you're angry,
and you insult Allah, you're not harming Allah.
You are harming yourself.
So,
when you harm
or negate
this spirit that Allah had planted into us,
in the long run,
you are harming
or we are harming
ourselves.
The breath of Allah
in Adam and Eve,
as well as the knowledge
taught by Allah to them,
were not given
their proper due.
But it was the recognition of this,
of this mistake,
that made Adam repent.
And as we all know,
is Allah the All-Merciful,
and in response
to this repentance,
Allah presented towards Adam,
gave words of revelation to him,
and more important for us now,
He promised mankind revelation
for the sending of a guidance.
In brief,
what Allah promised Adam and his descendants, the mankind,
all of us, are reminders.
And what are these reminders?
By definition,
a reminder is something
to come to act in forgetfulness.
Because man was created weak, that is, he was not created as a god.
And therefore, he forgets.
But Allah's most necessary mechanisms,
there are as follows:
descending of prophets.
These are forms of reminders.
They are what you call, remembrancers.
The prophet Muhammad is called a remembrancer.
Revelations are veritable reminders.
The Quran is the perfect reminder.
And Salat is a technique not to forget,
which means the same.
I say that Salat Prayer is a technique to keep on reminding us.
And you will find in Sura 20, verse 14,
in Sura 76, verses 25-26.
Thus, Shaytan (Satan)
as the source of forgetfulness
is an enemy of prophets.
Shaytan (Satan) is an enemy of revelation.
Shaytan (Satan) is an enemy of the Quran.
And Shaytan (Satan) is the greatest enemy of Salat.
One of his main jobs on earth is precisely
to make man forget all of these things that
we have just mentioned.
But now,
getting tired of talking about Shaytan (Satan),
let's go back to
the breath of Allah.
Let's relate the breath of Allah and His teaching of the names to Adam
to the purpose
of man's creation.
Quran says, in Sura 6, verse 102,
in Sura 20, verse 14,
in Sura 51, verse 56, and so on
It's very clear
that Allah created man
to worship
or serve Him.
The word here, Arabic word, the verb is
Abada (عبد),
to serve.
This reveals immediately to us
that creation is purposive.
And one of the meanings of Haq (حق)
when Allah is called Al-Haq (الحق)
is that He creates with a purpose.
And since Allah creates with a purpose,
certainly,
He must in some way or another reveal to man
the nature of this purpose.
Either
by putting in man's nature
a kind of primeval knowledge or by revelation.
For example,
if you get, you want to be a house,
well, you get a carpenter and you'll bring him to the land.
Well, it's just the same.
What will do?
What's it going to be? A brick house, a wooden house
or a house made (unintelligible) or no.
You have to tell and that is if you are, if you are rational,
and if you are in a purposive manner, you have to tell someone,
that carpenter what he's supposed to know.
You just (unintelligible).
Same thing with Allah.
We have (unintelligible)
Since He asked you the purpose, that He already put His mechanism in our nature.
If that is the case, which is the case, it is part of man's nature already to recognize Allah.
But more than that, Allah gives us revelation. If He doesn't give us the knowledge,
at least the propensity to accept such knowledge, when prophets appear. And thus, again, I submit to you all
that in giving man part of His breath, and in instilling in him the capacity
or potentialities to actualize certain qualities, now this is very important,
Allah makes it a duty for man to understand the names and to make such potentialities operative
or functional in the individual and social life. Now, this is a very strong statement.
That is, I repeat, if God has given you the capacity to be compassionate,
and if God has given us the capacity to become patient, ergo, it follows, it is a duty for us to be compassionate and to be patient.
Now, this is a very strong stance. I don't know what ethical philosophers say about this.
But if it's part of man's nature, because he has the breath of Allah, and Allah is compassionate,
when He breathed unto us, He gave us the capacity to be compassionate. Therefore, it's a duty for us
to develop our capacity for compassion, and certainly for knowledge. Allah is the Knower.
And if Allah has given us the power to know, it becomes our duty to know.
Therefore, again, it is part of worship, or part of service to Allah
to know what Allah is, who He is, what He is, what He represents, and to know more why He created us.
But more than that, as I mentioned earlier, it is part of Ibada (عباده),
of worship, to develop those capacities which Allah has given us.
But, as we discussed in the last Khutba, (unintelligible), and mankind for that matter
use such capacities in a manner showing lack of restraint. We forget.
In brief, powers, capacities can be misused or abused.
Therefore, I'll give you an example.
The capacity for patience sometimes can be used as a trick for revenge.
But that's not what Allah wants us.
Compassion also can be used as a technique to deceive people. Therefore, it's not real compassion.
Therefore, it now becomes clear to all of us why instructions must come from Allah Himself
regarding the use of such powers, the ends of such powers.
This is one of the fundamental meanings of revelation.
And if man has no free will, there will be no problem.
If man has no free will, he will be just acting A following B, following C, following D. But no.
Man has alternatives by the nature of his free will.
And it is this will
that can strengthen his potentialities or actualize his potentialities towards selfish or wrong ends.
Therefore, it is important for us to have revelation.
And he or she who looks to Allah as the source of revelation will have Allah responding to such person.
And Allah will give the correct guidance.
The position of Allah's breath in man is a test.
It is a test, as I've been repeating and over repeating, on how we should
develop our potentialities and have them directed properly.
And Allah has given us the document, how to actualize this potentialities and lead it
towards the destiny that He has created for us.
The more we develop our potentialities for the good, that is,
the more we develop our potentialities in accordance with Allah's guidance, the more our spirit grows,
which is the same as saying, the more of Allah's breath in us is working. All right?
I think this is our tautology. It's like saying A is equal to A, or one plus one is equal to two.
The more we develop our potentialities which Allah gave us for the good,
that is, the more we are listening or remembering Allah, the more is our spirit growing.
And since the spirit is the highest form of our soul, the more is our soul growing.
Now, Ustaz (teacher) has been emphasizing about the growth of our soul.
I'm sure he has his own profound meaning of what's meant by our soul growth.
I'm only giving one meaning, one possible meaning of what it means to say that the soul grows.
To me, the soul growth means that this highest proportion that comes from Allah, the spirit,
is growing or actualized.
So, to put it politically, the more of Allah's spirit you have in you, the more of divine elements you have in you.
The more we remember Allah and do what this remembrance and takes in action, the more
that the soul grows.
Right?
Because the more of Allah's spirit is in us.
Therefore, the more spiritual we become.
So, to say in Islam, so-and-so is spiritual has a particular meaning,
let us not confuse it with what other people, you know, say about so-and-so is spiritual.
We see that with these transcendental,
what do you call, people who follow transcendental meditation, "oh, this is very spiritual."
Well, I'm not the one who's going to fight with these people about the use of the word spiritual.
They have their own meaning, what spiritual means.
The Jews and the Christians, I assume, have also the meaning of spirituality.
But in terms of the Quran, we have a meaning for what is spiritual.
To us, spiritual will mean what?
The more of Allah's spirit in us.
And what does this mean?
Very clear.
The more we remember Allah, understand His names,
understand the manifestation of His names in nature, without and within us.
And therefore, we can conclude easily, the less we remember Allah, the more our soul will shrink.
That is the less of His spirit will be (unintelligible), right?
And off to put it another way. The less we remember Allah, the more His breath in us is stifled.
We are not allowing it to, to actualize.
And thus, we can now give a deeper meaning to the word righteousness or Taqwa (تقوا).
It is this.
Taqwa (تقوا) can mean, righteousness can mean to us now, a consistent and persevering consciousness
of Allah, Subhanahu Wa Ta'ala.
In Sura 91, verses 7 to 10, there is a description of the growth of the soul.
And it says that the growing soul is the soul that knows the difference between right and wrong.
The assumption is that the person is following the right.
In Sura 62, verse 2, the Quran speaks of the functions of messengers.
Messengers come to help men grow,
not grow physically,
to grow spiritually.
In Sura 2, verse 129, Ibrahim prays to Allah.
He prays to Allah to send messengers
to teach Muslims in spiritual and in wisdom,
and to teach man what man does not know.
In Sura 2, verse 151, it's clearly shown that growth, growth means growth of the soul.
It means knowledge of the spiritual, number one.
It means gaining wisdom,
or acquiring wisdom from such a knowledge of the spiritual and important,
coming to know what man did not know before,
or what man cannot know through his own efforts.
It is knowledge that can come only through the help of Allah.
And if we go to Sura 62, verses 2 to 4, and Sura 4, verse 113,
here we know deeper the meaning of Allah's infinite or boundless grace,
for it consists precisely in giving mankind these three things.
And you all know what this is. It refers to the greatest name, Zulfazl Al-Azim (ذُو ٱلْفَضْلِ ٱلْعَظِيمِ).
Allah is called Zulfazl Al-Azim (ذُو ٱلْفَضْلِ ٱلْعَظِيمِ) because His infinite grace consists precisely in
teaching us the spiritual, allowing us to have wisdom from following the spiritual.
In other words, we can say one of the greatest gifts of Allah is precisely giving us the techniques to counteract forgetfulness,
so that we do not fall into the trap of poor ancestor, Adam.
Now, it also becomes easier for us to understand what the Quran means when it says,
that those who forget Allah, forget their souls.
That is 59, Sura 59:19.
Do you see how, how beautiful the Quran is?
It's very consistent.
Those who forget Allah, forget their souls.
As I told you earlier, you cannot know Allah unless Allah gives you the power to know Him.
Allah is so great, no one, nothing can know Allah,
unless Allah Himself puts something in him or that thing to know Him.
This is the meaning of knowledge,
a contact between the Knower and the known,
and the relation of knowledge.
Allah had given us the power to know Him.
But those who insist in rejecting Allah,
who in effect, even if they say Allah, Allah, Allah, 20,000 times a day,
if they don't mean it, they forget their souls.
Why?
For the soul, as we've mentioned so many times,
is the most important part of man.
It is the part the man which represents part of Allah, spirit in him.
Therefore, to say that Mr. X forgets Allah,
is the same as saying that Mr. X forgets his soul.
This is again another tautology.
It's like saying A is A, or 1+1 is 2.
In Sura 20:124, it says,
that he who forgets Allah will be blind in the Last Day.
And the same Sura 20, verse 136 says,
that those who forget Allah's revelations will be forgotten by Allah in the Last Day.
Same thing in Sura 45, verse 34.
All this means,
that such individuals will be lost in the Last Day.
It also means,
that their souls have shrunk,
and for all practical purposes, disappeared.
They are just pure clay.
It also means,
that the most essential part...
... from other forms of clay.
Before Adam, he forgot.
But Alhamdu Lillah,
he was able to remember again.
He was fast, I suppose so.
Good for him and for his descendant.
For when he found that he was abandoned by Shaytan (Satan),
he immediately turned to Allah.
And Allah gives him and mankind the instruments to counteract forgetfulness.
This is up to us.
Well, I don't know really how fast Adam repented.
Maybe, I've been (unintelligible) those tasks when he says,
Repent fast! Did you say last time?
Did you say, repent fast?
By the way, with your permission, I would like to tell you a story.
You know, the Arabs, they are very interesting and wonderful people.
They have many proverbs and stories.
They combine Quran with common law, what they call Urs or Adat,
and tell you stories, but you put, they put them very nicely.
And there's a story which I don't remember very well.
They say there are about six things or seven things that a man can do in a hurry.
I'll put it another way.
The Arab says, take it easy in everything. Don't hurry,
except in around six or seven things.
I don't remember the six or seven things.
But I read it many years ago.
But this is what I remember.
The Arabs say, go slow except when you commit a sin, immediately ask repentance from Allah.
And you can see, this is Quranic.
Number two,
when your guests come to your house,
and they are hungry, immediately feed them.
Don't take it easy.
This is Arab. This is Arab hospitality.
The third one is, if you owe a person's money, please pay your debts.
This is common sense.
Before the (unintelligible), when a man dies,
hurry up to this barrier before he stinks.
And one of them, I think the last one, I forgot, is
if you have a young pretty virgin daughter,
marry her fast, don't wait,
before the value of the price, the Mahr, goes down.
But anyhow, to go back to, to go back to the Khutba,
here we can see that the Fãtehah really summarizes very well everything that we have said,
that Allah is the Lord of the worlds,
the Creator therefore of mankind,
but the Master of the Day of Judgment.
We need His help and guidance.
And we pray to Him for it.
In other words, we assume, we accept from Him that we need His help,
and therefore we want His revelation.
And we pray to Him that we should not be among the disbelievers and hypocrites.
They have forgotten Allah.
Even if they say Allah, Allah, Allah,
disbelievers and the hypocrites, for all practical purposes,
are saying with their mouths what their hearts denies.
They do not fear Him. They do not fear Allah.
They do not accept Him as Lord.
They do not accept Him as Judge.
And we pray to Allah that He help us remember Him.
And there's a very beautiful verse in Quran,
I don't know what's the number.
Allah says,
[2:152]  ... remember Me, ...
and I will remember you.
[2:152]  ... be thankful unto Me; ...
and do not belong to those who deny, to the disbelievers.
(2:152) فَٱذْكُرُونِىٓ أَذْكُرْكُمْ وَٱشْكُرُوا لِى وَلَا تَكْفُرُونِ
A'uzu Billahi Mina Shaytani Rajim
Bism Allah Arrahman Arraheem
اللهم اغفر لِلْمُؤْمِنِينَ والمؤمنات والمسلمين والمسلمات الاحياء منهم والاموات
رَبَّنَآ ءَاتِنَا فِى ٱلدُّنْيَا حَسَنَةً وَفِى ٱلْـَٔاخِرَةِ حَسَنَةً وَقِنَا عَذَابَ ٱلنَّارِ (2:201)
(33:41) يَٓأَيُّهَا ٱلَّذِينَ ءَامَنُوا ٱذْكُرُوا ٱللَّهَ ذِكْرًا كَثِيرًا
Dean Majul: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Allahu Akbar. Allahu Akbar. Ash-hadu Alla Elaha Ella Allah.
Hayya Alal Salat. Hayya Alal Falah.
Dr. Khalifa: Qad Qamat Al-Salat.
Allahu Akbar. Allahu Akbar.
Dean Majul: (unintelligible)
Audience: (unintelligible)
Dean Majul: Right. (unintelligible) of another one.
Dean Majul: (unintelligible)
Audience: (unintelligible)
A man: Cause I figured (unintelligible)
Dean Majul: (unintelligible)
Audience: (unintelligible)
A man: How are you doing?
A man: Good.
A man: Yourself?
A man: Alhamdu Lillah.
Audience: (unintelligible)
A woman: Yeah, they might be a little (unintelligible)
Dean Majul: (unintelligible)
Audience: (unintelligible)